so this is from the end goodwinica and
it's called flies
and the blessed one says because this
morning I dressed took my bowling robe
and entered Varanasi for Elms while
walking for Elms near the kettle yoking
fig tree
I saw a dissatisfied biku seeking
gratification outwardly model
muddle-minded confused without clear
comprehension uncomposed with a
Wandering mind and loose sense faculties
having seen him I said to that Baku Baku
do not pollute yourself it is inevitable
that flies will pursue and attack one
who has polluted himself
and being tainted by a stench hmm
then being exhorted to thus that Baker
acquired a sense of urgency
when this was said to certain biku asked
to this one what bante is meant by
pollution what is this tension what are
the Flies
he says longing is what is meant by
pollution polluting yourself your will
is the stench bad and wholesome thoughts
of Lies it is inevitable that flies will
pursue and attack one who has polluted
himself and been tainted by a stench
so you can have these unwholesome
thoughts is repetitive evil thoughts of
lust of your will why is that why are
these flies there hmm
yeah so how do you deal with the Flies
you tried to kill every fly individually
preventing the thoughts dealing with
them antidoting them managing them
removing them or remove the reason why
they're coming back
ill will longing lust distraction remove
that these thoughts will stop coming we
keep saying that yeah
you don't want to feel that's how you
abandon them yeah you have flies abandon
you by removing that Which flies want
the stench yeah and you maintain the
stench you maintain the pollution by
acting out by not being restrained by
nothing during things on the right level
that's exactly how you maintain craving
and longing and aversion to its pain and
wanting pleasure all the reasons that
these flies keep coming back
so God just sends those to take the
context don't act out and do things on
the right level
and flies will still come
and they can come back
if you if you lose your behavior if you
start reacting if you start basically
accruing again the stench accumulating
the stench and and the Flies will come
back
it doesn't need to be done accidentally
sure it can be done carelessly but
because you kept choosing to act out and
go back to desires and lose your sense
restraint and abandon the context and
give into distraction and so on
so then the Flies will come back
but if you're of the view that the Flies
are the problem and you must be dealing
with the Flies
you know through concentrating in this
and that and method to stop thinking and
and all these like practices and you
know whatever people misunderstand from
the suit is then
you're still not emptying the rubbish
because of which the Flies are coming
they're just chasing the Flies more
vehemently you're putting up these
barriers uh external barriers sure Nets
and then borders machines and the
repellents but fundamentally yeah while
the very problem is the thing that's
putting up the borders and yeah that's
where the bad smell is yeah
tell us when you can spend the whole
life of management successful to a
degree
skilled with protected circumstances and
so on fundamentally no you're still in
the same domain
so if you have thoughts available the
thoughts of last and I must get through
this is the problem no that's the
symptom of the problem those thoughts
are there because your mind has the
sediment times
and in the suitors as well
frequently Ponders and dwells on things
that are attracting lust lustful
thoughts and angry thoughts and thoughts
available and thoughts of distraction
so don't frequently Ponder on those
themes what themes well themes of
pleasure is valuable themes of a version
of pain is Justified themes of these
things belong to me and I you know I
feel entitled to act out and be free
from suffering and get this and get my
John and get whatever else I don't want
to deal with this
the themes of I the themes of mine
all these themes that are contradictory
to the universal natural experience
those strong views
yeah they're perpetuating your attitudes
of dirt the attitudes of longing the
attitude of aversion
yeah that stage wanting wanting pleasure
aversion to pain
and as it comes out of those those
fundamental cravings
you can't start the cleansing if you not
if you have that wrong view that it is
the world that is making me it's the
flies that made me think yeah yeah no
and that's why yeah that's not where the
stage is that's the symptom of the
stench if there flies means or there is
something and again
colloquially
flies keep coming back I better check
this room I better check this building
something they keep coming back for
but if you can't even admit that yeah
you don't have that mundane right here
yeah if you wouldn't admit that because
it's just too much aversion towards
flies
I must get rid of it
and I must get rid of it I'm just
getting through it that's where the
problem is
and then the idea of what meditation is
it sort of follows out of that okay let
me just concentrate when I'm not aware
of these things anymore when I stop
hitting the Flies
that's how I'm free from it no this is
how you learn how to concentrate and
look away from them
just you know see where the stench is
coming from
accepting that the Flies are there
because of yes it's so not wasting not
perpetuating your views of trying to
deal with the Flies but actually focus
of okay presence of Lies means
simultaneous presence of the of the of
the that Which flies that attracted to
so lastful thoughts cannot come cannot
exist cannot assail me
can I cannot be liable to them unless
there is a simultaneously present state
of loss for mind where is that lustful
mind it's not on the level of the Flies
and thoughts it's on the level of signs
and features as we said before so how do
I discern that what do I look for
what do I need to do in that sense but
yeah if if all you do is feel Justified
about dealing with the flies through all
sorts of you know management management
techniques and concentrations and so on
then yeah there's none of this can apply
to them
but that scene where the problem is
that's
close to the right view you know that
mundane it's so it's yeah sure you know
it's almost it's kind of necessary for
it right yeah if you don't even see
where the problem is you won't be able
to learn how to do things rightly
for your endurance would just be okay I
just have to put up with these flies and
do nothing
no you still got to do something but it
mustn't be aimed at the Flies
so but all I see is flies and doing
something towards flies well exactly so
you need to learn how else to do
something without doing what you take
for granted to be done deal with the
Flies do the things that bother me
the middle way yeah but if you're not if
you're going to be trying to deal with
things all time manage things which are
not the actual problem yeah
as even if you're doing the the Buddhist
so-called
according your techniques and your
message yeah sure sure
whatever
you're not doing it on the right level
yeah
and then in a more in a very dangerous
situation so because now you're
establishing that
for yourself as the way out of suffering
when in fact yeah
and then you feel even more justified in
managing it and dealing with the Flies
and preventing flies from coming
not by removing the bait but by setting
up further traps and controlling the
environment and avoiding things that
disturb you and you saw
how does one get the right of you
by not dealing with the Flies
taking this by reflecting on what where
the problem is
although you know everything all my
senses are pointing me it's because of
this this is why I'm not told this if
I'm angry
that's not what it would have said
the root of suffering is craving not to
the world not things in the world not
sense objects not senses not to not your
thoughts
it's the craving in regard to what is
felt so that's always on me
and that's exactly why the Right View
starts with understanding what suffering
is
presence of craving means presence of
suffering not presence of lies or
presence of this or that so what is that
craving that I need to understand well
if you if you discern it understand it
uh seed signs and features
that is the Right View
you saw the cause of suffering truly
correctly accurately
then you will know exactly what the
escape from it is
you wouldn't need to figure that out
as a next step of something seeing the
presence of craving is okay so absence
absence of suffering regardless of the
Flies and the circumstances
so what
how can I have that craving always
absent and that's the noble level path
you might not see it in eight terms as
the Buddha described it but you would
see exactly what that path is in the
broad Strokes ah sensory strength
guarding of the sense doors not acting
out enduring things on the right level
until this gratuit is aversion towards
discomfort is abandoned which is craving
the truth is a version to the discomfort
that you take for granted is your
craving
gratuitous Delight towards Comfort is
your craving that's how there's no a
thing a craving that you can witness
with your senses it's always the
background context that's maintained
through careless attitude of
pleasure I'm leaning towards
just just by default no reason and the
reason is you haven't
considered well
thoroughly frequently often enough that
leaning towards pleasure is actually
dangerous that's the danger not present
or absence of pleasure in the world and
everything in my cup no it's leaning is
the Trap accepting that attitude is how
it attract
leaning away from Pain just gratuitously
no not wanting it
it's like why oh because you never
really considered it thoroughly on that
level
like leaning towards that's the longing
leaning away that's diversion of tension
yeah that's the stench
and in the suffering the Flies flies the
Flies that's all the consequences of it
so now so if there is no leaning there
will be no flies
if there is no leaning towards pleasure
there would be no lust of thoughts if
there is no leaning away from pain I
aversion craving there would be no Angry
thoughts no thoughts available no
thoughts of discomfort or discontent
that's all right thoughts and hindrances
having us are the symptoms of the
problem
of Ukraine
so this is the the verse at the end of
that Suitor
and it says the Flies thoughts based on
lust will run in pursuit of one
unrestrained in the sense of faculties
unguarded
a bigger who is polluted tainted by a
stench is far from the banner and reaps
only distress
whether in the village or the forest the
unwise foolish person not having gained
peace for himself goes around followed
by flies
but those accomplished in virtuous
Behavior whose Delight in wisdom and
peace
who Delight in wisdom and peace those
peaceful ones live happily having
destroyed the Flies
having destroyed the planning staff then
no away
they'll die away